A Guide to the Virginia Wilderness Committee Collection, 1969-2009
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
- Thomas Jefferson National Forest
  - Supervisor Reports, 1970s-1998 (Box-folder 3:20)
  - Wilderness Resource Management Conference, 1986 (Box-folder 3:21)
  - Jefferson Roadless Area Inventory, 1994-1997 (Box-folder 3:22)
  - Citizens for Southwest Virginia (Box-folder 3:23)
  - Radford Group, 2001-2002 (Box-folder 3:24)
  - TJ Plan Hearings, Aug. 23-24, 2002 (Box-folder 3:25)
  - 1999 Citizens Workshops, Aug., Oct. 1999 (Box-folder 3:26)
  - TJ Plan, "Rolling Alternative ", 1995, 1999 (Box-folder 3:27)
  - TJ Forest Draft Plan, 2003 (Box-folder 3:28)
  - Appalachian Power Company in TJ, 1994-1996 (Box-folder 3:29)
  - Justin Askins, 1999 (Box-folder 3:30)
  - Bear Town and Bear Hole Hollow Road, 1986-1998 (Box-folder 3:31)
  - Bland County National Recreation Area (Box-folder 3:32)
  - Brush Mountain East, 2001-2002 (Box-folder 3:33)
  - Brush Mountain, Montgomery Co., 2002-2005 (Box-folder 3:34)
  - Brushy Mountain, Bland Co. (Box-folder 3:35)
  - Cave Springs/Stone Mountain, 2002, 2006 and undated (Box-folder 3:36)
  - Cove Mountain Lake Unit, 1986-1972 (Box-folder 3:37)
  - Crawfish Valley/Bear Creek, Bland, Smyth, Wythe Cos., 2003 (Box-folder 3:38)
  - Devil's Fork, Straight Fork, 1977, 1996, 1998 and undated (Box-folder 3:39)
  - Garden Mountain, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 3:40)
  - High Knob National Recreation Area (Box-folder 3:41)
  - Hoop Hole, North Mountain, North Creek, 2001 and undated (Box-folder 3:42)
  - Hunting Camp Creek/Little Wolf Creek, Bland County, 1991-2006 (Box-folder 3:43)
  - James River Face, 2006 (Box-folder 3:44)
  - Jennings Creek, 14973-1976 (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Kimberling Creek, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Little Walker Mountain, Pulaski, Wythe, Bland Cos., 2001, 2003 (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Long Spur, 1991, 2001 (Box-folder 4:4)
    ‐ Contains floppy disc: Longspur description in Word Perfect and Microsoft Word.
  - Lynn Camp Map, 2006 (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Mill Creek, 1981 (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Mountain Lake, 1977-1994, Maps (Box-folder 4:7)
  - Mountain Lake, 1977-1994, Meeting Minutes and Correspondence (Box-folder 4:8)
  - Mountain Lake, 1977-1994, Proposals (Box-folder 4:9)
  - Mountain Lake, 1977-1994, Peter's Mountain (Box-folder 4:10)
  - Mt. Rogers National Recreation Area locations, 1979-2003 (Box-folder 4:11)
  - Mt. Rogers NRA jurisdiction, 1970s-1990s (Box-folder 4:12)
  - Mt. Rogers – Salamander Info (Box-folder 4:13)
  - North Fork of the Pound, Wise Co. (Box-folder 4:14)
  - Peter's Mountain, 1987 (Box-folder 4:15)
  - Poverty Creek, 1971 (Box-folder 4:16)
  - Roaring Branch Map, 1979 (Box-folder 4:17)
  - Shawvers Run and Barbours Creek, 1990 (Box-folder 4:18)
  - Thunder Ridge, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 4:19)
  - Upper Craig Creek, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 4:20)
- VWC Projects/Interests/Activities
  - New Virginia Wilderness Campaign, 1990 (Box-folder 4:21)
    ‐ handwritten notes, 1990 rough draft for Little River Wilderness proposal, proposal to Congress by VWC, newsletters and correspondence.
  - Arctic National Wildlife Refuge, 1978-2003 (Box-folder 4:22)
    ‐ newsletters, reports, newspaper clippings, correspondence.
  - Back Bay/Knotts Island, Virginia vs. North Carolina, 1970s (Box-folder 4:23)
    ‐ correspondence, newspaper clippings, case studies, newsletters.
  - Proposed Nestle plant at Big Springs, 2003 (Box-folder 4:24)
    ‐ all newspaper clippings.
  - Chesapeake Bay Preservation, 1984 and 1999 (Box-folder 4:25)
    ‐ correspondence, study summary, newspaper articles.
  - Virginia Clean Air Now campaign of 1999, 1999 (Box-folder 4:26)
    ‐ campaign updates, correspondence, maps.
  - Cushaw Project, 2006 (Box-folder 4:27)
    ‐ boat regulation printouts of PowerPoint slides, maps, statement by J. J. Murray, executive summary.
  - Endangered Species, 2005 (Box-folder 4:28)
    ‐ correspondence, notes, outline for Animal Extinctions Symposium.
  - Governor's Council on the Environment, 1970s (Box-folder 4:29)
    ‐ copy of amendment, statements/announcements, "Environmental Agency Reorganization in Virginia" by David Favre, correspondence, "An Analysis of Alternatives for Achieving Environmental Coordination in Virginia" (draft) by Joseph B. Tompkins, Jr., newspaper clipping.
  - Gypsy Moth Report, 1973 (Box-folder 4:30)
    ‐ contains two reports, one in brochure form, the other a typewritten document.
  - Peter Kirby and Southern Appalachian Wilderness Walk, 1999 (Box-folder 4:31)
    ‐ newspaper clippings, brochures, flyers, memo, correspondence, proposal, schedule for Wilderness Walk in TJNF.
  - Lucas v. South Carolina Coastal Council, 1992 (Box-folder 4:32)
    ‐ case analysis.
  - Mollusks, 1970s (Box-folder 4:33)
    ‐ educational information, brochure, articles and other scholarly publications.
  - Mueller proposal (Box-folder 4:34)
    ‐ email correspondence, newspaper clipping.
  - United States Department of the Interior Natural Areas, 1970s (Box-folder 4:35)
    ‐ Audobon Society brochure, proposal, correspondence.
  - Virginia's Natural Heritage Program - brochure (Box-folder 4:36)
  - National Park Services, 1970-1973 (Box-folder 4:37)
    ‐ brochure, correspondence, Potential Natural Landmark Identification form.
  - Southern Pine Beetle, 1987 (Box-folder 4:38)
    ‐ correspondence, Record of Decision from USDA Forest Service.
  - Stream Channelization, 1970s (Box-folder 4:39)
    ‐ brochures, newsletters, correspondence, case study.
  - Strip Mining for Coal, 1970s (Box-folder 4:40)
    ‐ correspondence, resolution/proposal, statement by A.T. Wright.
  - Sweet Briar Forest Logging, 2001 (Box-folder 4:41)
    ‐ correspondence, statement, map.
  - Wild Lands Project, 2000 (Box-folder 4:42)
    ‐ Wildlands site nomination form, Wildlands Network Design Workshop for the Chesapeake Bay Watershed Agenda and Goals, draft of background document, Wildlands Project Approach, correspondence, contribution to Design Workshop II.
  - Wilderness Week, 2006 (Box-folder 4:43)
    ‐ business cards, schedule of events, notes, outline, correspondence, Support H.R.3603, The Central Idaho Economic Development and Recreation Act, Documents pertaining to Wilderness Week, which seems to be a lobbying effort in D.C. and wilderness legislation.
  - Wind Power, 2003 (Box-folder 4:44)
    ‐ draft for Wind Turbines in West Virginia, correspondence (letters, email, fax), Phase I Avian Risk Assessment for the Mount Storm Wind Power Project, Migration Study at the Backbone Mountain Wind, other proposals and studies related to wind power.
  - Gas & Oil lines, 1993-2000 (Box-folder 4:45)
    ‐ correspondence, decision notice about Thornwood gas pipeline, memoranda, maps, newsletters and newspaper clippings, brochures.
  - Monongahela National Forest, 1971 (Box-folder 5:1)
    ‐ newspaper clipping, letter from The Wilderness Society (Ernie Dickerman).
  - FS Land Sale, 2006 (Box-folder 5:2)
    ‐ correspondence, "The President’s Billion Dollar Public Land Sell off Scheme", maps.
  - Air Quality, 2001 (Box-folder 5:3)
    ‐ correspondence, "Power That Pollutes" publication by Southern Environmental Lawn Center, Senate report, testimony before House.
  - Support for Purchase of Burkes Garden, 1971 (Box-folder 5:4)
    ‐ correspondence.
  - Proposed Carr Mountain Trail, 2007 (Box-folder 5:5)
    ‐ one map.
  - Wilderness Leaders Meeting and Campaigns in the 21st century (Box-folder 5:6)
    ‐ meeting outline, notes, participants list with contact information, "Wilderness Campaigns in the 21st Century", reflections by Bart Koehler.
  - Senator Frank Church Hearings, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 5:7)
    ‐ letter, "A University View of the Forest Service", 1970 document, Congressional Record, November 19, 1970.
  - Doug Colman and Wintergreen (Box-folder 5:8)
    ‐ newspaper clipping, two letters.
  - General Wilderness Economics Information, 2001-2003 (Box-folder 5:9)
    ‐ two publications by the Outdoor Industry Foundation, economic profiles, one publication by The Wilderness Society, one publication by the Southern Appalachian Forest Coalition.
  - Eminent Domain, 1970s (Box-folder 5:10)
    ‐ two letters.
  - General Wilderness Visitor Ethics (Box-folder 5:11)
    ‐ two brochures.
  - Virginia Flood Plains, 1970s (Box-folder 5:12)
    ‐ "Proceedings: Community Workshop on Flood Insurance," Flood Damage Abatement Study, newspaper clippings.
  - Forestry in America (Box-folder 5:13)
    ‐ 1 publication, reprinted from American Forests.
  - Off Road Vehicles in National Forests, 1970s (Box-folder 5:14)
    ‐ brochure, comments on off-road vehicle alternatives, maps, Virginia Wilderness Committee position paper on the use of off-road vehicles, draft position paper, correspondence.
  - President Clinton's Initiative, 1999 (Box-folder 5:15)
    ‐ proposal, newspaper clipping.
  - Water Quality, 1996 (Box-folder 5:16)
    ‐ 2 news clippings.
  - The Wilderness Society Guide to Wilderness Designation (Box-folder 5:17)
    ‐ candidates lists, correspondence, printed copy of "Why Wilderness."
  - Virginia Scenic Rivers/National Wild and Scenic Rivers System, 1970s (Box-folder 5:18)
    ‐ Virginia Scenic Rivers Study, U.S. Dept of the Interior memorandum, brochure, newspaper clipping, correspondence, public notices, maps, recommendations (notes), Jefferson National Forest Wild and Scenic Rivers Eligibility Determinations.
  - Dismal Swamp (Box-folder 5:19)
    ‐ This folder was divided into two because of its size. It includes reports, issue of Contact, newspaper clippings, correspondence, brochures.
  - Dismal Swamp, continued (Box-folder 5:20)
    ‐ more reports, newspaper clippings, correspondence, maps.
  - Goshen Pass, 1972 (Box-folder 5:21)
    ‐ one letter, scans of newspaper clippings.
  - House Mountain, Rockbridge County, 1990 (Box-folder 5:22)
    ‐ one brochure, one letter to supporters.
  - Proposed Trails, Great Eastern Trail and Carr Mountain Trail (Box-folder 5:23)
    ‐ proposal, letter, map.
  - New River (Box-folder 5:24)
    ‐ letter from Sierra Club, statement before Federal Power Commission.
  - Virginia Mountain Treasures (Box-folder 5:25)
    ‐ correspondence, maps, memoranda, report by The Wilderness Society, "Virginia’s Mountain Treasures", two drafts of VMT report, handwritten notes.
  - Thomas Jefferson and George Washington Roadless Rule Defense Campaign (Box-folder 5:26)
    ‐ rule of 2001, protects roadless areas. Bush overhauls, Virginia committees trying to keep protection in Virginia, correspondence, article from periodical (Science magazine, volume 316), newspaper clippings, memoranda, Southern Roadless Campaign Action Campaign, Theodore Roosevelt Conservation Alliance Survey, Southern Environmental Law Center publication.
  - Shenandoah National Park, 1969-2003 (Box-folder 5:27)
    ‐ receipt, fact sheet, newspaper clippings, summary of the General Management Plan, correspondence, brochures, wildflower calendar, maps, proposals, memoranda.
  - Shenandoah Watershed Study, 2004 (Box-folder 5:28)
  - Federal Executive Institute (FEI) Conference, 1998 (Box-folder 5:29)
    ‐ Typed notes defining "wilderness", its uses, milestones, and possible candidates, Handwritten notes (seem to be from a speech?), F.E.I. at the top, "Wilderness Areas of the Virginia Mountains" – Shenandoah Natl. Park, GWNF, TJNF, "Some Good Candidates for Wilderness Designation", correspondence, (first draft) Public-Private Partnership in Land and Species Preservation by Bob Maranto, FEI, conference Itinerary draft, November 9, 1998 Program– "Competing Interests in Land Management: George Washington and Thomas Jefferson National Forest", Two copies, attached to both copies are biographies for program speakers and an article from Government Executive by Louis Jacobson called "Forest Fight" about logging debates, website printouts ("Issues Common to the National Forests in the Southern Appalachians") and maps.
- VWC Miscellaneous (Box-folder 5:30)
  ‐ This folder is for miscellaneous items that would not fit elsewhere. Such items include: a business card, correspondence, fliers, various newspaper clippings, committee reports, proposals.
- VWC Photo Series, 2000 (Box-folder 5:31)
  ‐ Contains 2000 Wilderness Bill photos; miscellaneous photos featuring wilderness areas.
- Jumpdrive (Box-folder 5:32)
  ‐ The donor provided a USB drive, which includes further information about the VWC. Some items were printed from the drive, and a sheet of paper is included in the folder to indicate which items from the drive were printed. Items printed are also listed below:
  ‐Bsumek - Framing the message.doc – "America's Wild Legacy, Message Memo, January 2007 ", 10pp
  ‐Carr - Carr-Kaine to Hyzer 08.doc – letter from Tim Kaine to Maureen Hyzer
  ‐Carr - Kaine Letter Nov 08.pdf – same letter as above but on letterhead
  ‐Correspondence - Blahblahblah.doc – letter to Mrs. P. Brown from J.J. Murray ‐Correspondence - David Hall.doc - letter to David Hall from J.J. Murray
  ‐Correspondence - Grijalva.doc – letter to President-elect Barack Obama from Laura Neale
  ‐Correspondence - Koehler 7Nov08.doc – letter to Bart from Jim
  ‐Correspondence - Progress 17Nov09.doc – letter to The Daily Progress from Elizabeth Murray
  ‐Correspondence - Richmond & Fishburne.doc – letter to Mr. Joseph W. Richmond, Jr. from J.J. Murray
  ‐Economics - County profiles [1].doc – four pages, profiles of Augusta, Highland and Rockingham counties
  ‐Economics - Protection Doc [1].doc – "George Washington National Forest: Land Protection for the Economy ", 3pp
  ‐Finance - 08 Report-CLM.doc – Fiscal Report for Carol Lena Miller, payments for 2008, treasurers report (2pp)
  ‐Finance - Accounts 08.doc – VWC -2008 Finances (2pp)
  ‐Finance - Exec Com Minutes 13Mar09.doc – VWC Executive Committee Meeting Minutes, 13 March 2009
  ‐Finance - Julie Memorial Fund.doc – Contributions to the Virginia Wilderness Committee in Honor of Juliana Maxine Hood Simpson (names and addresses), 2pp
  ‐Finance - Treas Rpt 1 Jan 10.doc – VWC Treasurer's Report, 1 January 2010
  ‐Finance - Treas Rpt June 09.doc – VWC Treasurer's Report, 1 January 2009-30 June 2009
  ‐Finance - VMT Invoice.doc – Letter to Melissa Giacchino from J.J. Murray and invoice
  ‐Finance - VWC.doc VWC 2008 finances
  ‐Finance - Waterman Appointment.doc – letter to Laura Proffitt of StellarOne, appointment of Karen Waterman to office of treasurer as a result of the death of Julie Simpson
  ‐Laura Neale - FS Letter Jan09.doc – four page letter draft to Maureen Hyzer from Laura Neale
  ‐Laura Neale - Report to the Wilderness Society 2008-2009-JJMrev.doc – three pages, report to the Wilderness Society and Wilderness Support Center, prepared by Laura Neale, President of VWC
  ‐Laurel Fork Directions - Laurel Fork Directions.doc – directions to a party on Lauren Fork
  ‐Mark - LaBare rebuttal.doc – "GW and Jefferson Nationals Forest Visitation and Economics "
  ‐Friends of Shenandoah - Commentsonplan3[1]-JJM.doc – letter to planning team (GW Plan Revision) from Lynn Cameron with comments from JJ Murray, 10 pgs
  ‐Friends of Shenandoah - FriendsMinutes1208[1].doc – 4 pgs, December 16, 2008, Friends of Shenandoah Mountain meeting minutes submitted by Lynn Cameron
  ‐Friends of Shenandoah - Matthews.doc – Forest by David Matthews
  ‐Friends of Shenandoah - MediaPlan 09.doc – Media planning meeting minutes, May 20, 2009; 3pp
  ‐Friends of Shenandoah - One-pager Jan09.doc – Shenandoah Mountain proposal
  ‐Friends of Shenandoah - SMendorsement[1].doc – Shenandoah Mountain proposal endorsement
  ‐Friends of Shenandoah - Supplemental%20letter[1].doc – November 26, 2008 letter to Planning Team
  ‐Friends of Shenandoah - WildVa-Laura response[1]].doc – 2pp, Laura Neale response to September 15 letter
  ‐Friends of Shenandoah - Zack Fields 8Dec08.doc – Meeting with Zach Fields, December 8, 2008
  ‐GW Plan - Alleghany Co - Peters Mt. Rd. Relocation Comments.doc – letter to Patrick Sheridan from J.J. Murray, April 28, 2009
  ‐GWwild - GW Plan (Different than above)- Laura Comments.doc – letter from Laura Neale to Maureen Hyzer, August 8, 2009
  ‐GWwild - GW Plan - RestoringCreationGWletter[1].doc – letter to Planning Team, August 8, 2008, on Restoring Creation House Church letterhead
  ‐GWwild - GW Plan - VWC-Final comments.doc – letter to Planning Team from Laura Neale
  ‐GWwild - Issues for Sept08.doc – 6pp, areas list
  ‐VMT - Conservation Designations.doc – 2pp, Conservation terms
  ‐VMT - DEDICATION-Rev3.doc – "Dedicated to the Honorable John William Warner, United States Senator from Virginia: 1978-2008
  ‐Waynesboro Group - Minutes 8Jan09.doc – Waynesboro Group meeting minutes, January 8, 2009, 3pp
  ‐Waynesboro Group - Notes-11July08.doc – Waynesboro Group meeting minutes, July 11, 2008; 2pp
  ‐Wyss - Wyss let 10Dec08.doc – letters to The Wyss Foundation from JJ Murray
  ‐Wyss - Wyss Annual Rpt 08.doc – 7 pp annual report
- Oversize Maps
  - Original Map Set, VWC Proposal, 2002 (Folder 1)
    - Atkins, Troutdale
    - Not labeled – Garden and Brushy Mountains
    - Troutdale, White Top, Konnarock
    - Cedar Springs
    - Cripple Creek
    - Speedwell
    - Looney, Craig Springs
    - Long Spur, Bland
    - Newport, McDonald's Mill
    - Long Spur, Pulaski
    - Garden Mountain
    - Rural Retreat, Nebo
    - Kimberling Creek, Rocky Gap
  - VWC Working Maps, c. 2003 (Folder 2)
    - Mt. Lake Addition
    - Peter's Mountain Addition
    - Brush Mountain, Kimberling Creek Additions
    - Whitetop Laurel
    - Mercy Branch
    - Hunting Camp Creek
    - Whitetop
    - Garden Mountain, Beartown Additions
    - Seng Mountain, Raccoon Branch
    - Brush Mountain
    - Brush Mountain East
    - Crawfish Valley
  - Forest Service Working Map Set, January 2004 (Folder 3)
    - Cave Springs
    - Little Dry Run Addition and Horse Heaven
    - Seng Mountain and Raccoon Branch
    - Hunting Camp/Little Wolf Creek and Garden Mountain
    - Little Walker Mountain
    - Long Spur
    - Lewis Fork Addition and Little Wilson Creek Additions
    - Beartown Additions
    - Bear Creek (South Half)
    - Bear Creek (North Half)
    - Kimberling Creek Additions and Brushy Mountain
    - Peter's Mountain Additions
    - Shawver's Rush Addition
    - Mountain Lake Additions (2 copies)
    - Brush Mountain
  - Forest Service Working Maps of VWC Proposals, July 2004 (Folder 4)
    - Mountain Lake Additions
    - Bear Creek (2 copies)
    - Peter's Mountain Addition (2 copies)
    - Shawvers Run Additions (2 copies)
    - Lewis Fork Addition and Little Wilson Creek Additions (2 copies)
    - Seng Mountain and Raccoon Branch (2 copies)
    - Stone Mountain (2 copies)
    - Brush Mountain and Brush Mountain East (2 copies)